<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>supernova | Tomás E. Müller Bravo</title>
    <link>https://temuller.github.io/tag/supernova/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://temuller.github.io/tag/supernova/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>supernova</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Tomás Müller `2021`</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://temuller.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>supernova</title>
      <link>https://temuller.github.io/tag/supernova/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>PISCOLA</title>
      <link>https://temuller.github.io/project/piscola/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://temuller.github.io/project/piscola/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;ython for &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;ntelligent &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;upernova &lt;strong&gt;CO&lt;/strong&gt;smology &lt;strong&gt;L&lt;/strong&gt;ight-curve &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;nalysis (&lt;strong&gt;PISCOLA&lt;/strong&gt;) is a code I have developed as part of my PhD to fit Type Ia supernova light curves in a data-driven way using Gaussian Process. The post analysis is done with Non-negative Matrix Factorization, a machine learning approach to extract features/parameters from the rest-frame light curves in order to do cosmology (Müller-Bravo et al., in prep.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Press the tag below to see more examples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Type II supernova fitting code</title>
      <link>https://temuller.github.io/project/snii_fit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://temuller.github.io/project/snii_fit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Type II supernova fitting code by Ondrej Pejcha. I contributed some minor modifications and am currently hosting the repository with the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Press the tag below to see more examples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PESSTO data-reduction pipeline</title>
      <link>https://temuller.github.io/project/pessto/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://temuller.github.io/project/pessto/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pipeline for the reduction of data from the New Technology Telescope (La Silla observatory, Chile). The original pipeline was developed by Stephano Valenti as part of the PESSTO collaboration. I am the current developer and manager of this pipeline as part of ePESSTO+ collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Press the tag below to see more examples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TESS SN Pipeline</title>
      <link>https://temuller.github.io/project/tess_sn_pipeline/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://temuller.github.io/project/tess_sn_pipeline/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Transitin Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) produces light curves with unprecedented cadence. This is ideal for studying supernovae, but there is not dedicated pipeline to extract and reduce the data of these transients. I have been working on this project with other people from the USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Press the tag below to see more examples&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> Judging a book by its cover: estimating red supergiant masses from their surface abundance</title>
      <link>https://temuller.github.io/post/astrobites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://temuller.github.io/post/astrobites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;See below a guest post I wrote for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobites.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Astrobites&lt;/a&gt;. For the original one 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobites.org/2019/01/28/judging-book-cover-red-supergiant/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1811.04087.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The surface abundances of Red Supergiants at core-collapse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ben Davies and Luc Dessart&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author&amp;rsquo;s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Astrophysics Research Institute, Liverpool John Moores University&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; accepted for publication in MNRAS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Core-Collapse supernovae (CCSNe) are explosions coming from massive stars (above 8 solar masses) when they reach the end of their life. A 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://astronomy.swin.edu.au/cosmos/T/Type&amp;#43;II&amp;#43;Supernova&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Type II-P Supernova&lt;/a&gt; (SN II-P)  is a common type of CCSN which shows a &amp;ldquo;plateau&amp;rdquo; in its light curve, driven by a Hydrogen-rich envelope. Observations of the explosion site of some of these objects have shown that the progenitors of these explosions are 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://aasnova.org/2018/01/03/astrophysics-of-red-supergiants/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Red Supergiant&lt;/a&gt; (RSG) stars. From these data several predictions can be made by comparing with stellar evolution models. One test that can be made is to determine the initial mass of the progenitor (the mass at the Main-Sequence), which can be done by comparing the luminosity of the progenitor with model predictions. Another way is to measure the mass of the Hydrogen-rich envelope by modelling the light curve and making some assumptions about the core mass. A different way is to measure 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobites.org/guides/spectroscopy-and-spectral-lines/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;spectral lines&lt;/a&gt; of some elements, like Oxygen, at late time (more than 120 days after the explosion, approximately), which correlates with the initial mass as shown by some models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, these methods do not agree in general, so a proper estimation of the initial mass of the progenitor of a SN II-P can not be made. Having this in mind, the authors of the article proposed a different way of estimating the initial mass by measuring the surface composition (or surface abundance) of the progenitor star at early epochs (less than 1 day approximately). There are two main reasons for this: firstly, at this stage some spectral features are easy to identify, and secondly, the surface abundance is not expected to suffer from explosive mixing at early time, which erases any link to the progenitor mass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test this, the authors make use of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://mesa.sourceforge.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MESA&lt;/a&gt; code to study sets of evolutionary models. The evolution across the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://astronomy.swin.edu.au/cosmos/H/Hertzsprung-Russell&amp;#43;Diagram&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hertzsprung-Russell&lt;/a&gt; (H-R) diagram is key to understand the different processes and phases a star goes through, so the authors use MESA to evolve stars with different initial masses to study this. As it can be seen in Figure 1, less massive stars cross the H-R diagram more rapidly than more massive star, which means that more massive stars have more time to dredge up material from the inner layers into the surface (mixing the abundances) before the end of the RSG phase. Another factor that has to be taken into account is the mass loss. In general, more massive star loose more mass than the least massive ones, so their outer envelopes are thinner compared to the total size of the star, hence their surface abundances suffer from more mixing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Fig1.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fig. 1: H-R diagram for stars with different initial masses as labelled. The circles mark evenly-spaced time steps. The stars indicate the beginning of the RSG phase. More massive stars take longer to cross the H-R diagram than less massive stars.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the surface abundance can not be directly measured, an indirect way of measurement was developed. The authors demonstrate that the surface abundance can be estimated by measuring the ratio between spectral lines, specifically the Carbon-to-Nitrogen ratio, a few hours after the supernova explosion. They simulate early time supernova spectra coming from stars with three different initial masses. The results of these simulated spectra are shown in Figure 2 for a 15 and 25 solar masses stars, for three epochs: 3.1, 12.0 and 24.0 hours after the explosion. One can clearly see the greater strength of Nitrogen lines in the higher mass model, and the greater strength of Carbon and Oxygen lines in the lower mass model. These same trends have been seen in the observed early-time spectra of SN II-P, however, the lack of data at these early stages is clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Fig2.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fig. 2: Early-time SN II-P spectra for progenitors of 15 (blue) and 25 (red) solar masses. From top to bottom, spectra of 3.1, 12.0 and 24.0 hours after explosion. It can be seen the difference in the strengths of lines for the two progenitors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the other methods mentioned above, the surface abundance method suffers from several uncertainties, but no further comparison is given. Finally, the author estimate that within the next decade several early time spectra of SN II-P should be available, which would help decreasing the uncertainties for a better estimation of the initial masses of their progenitors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
