<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>astronomy | Tomás E. Müller Bravo</title>
    <link>https://temuller.github.io/tag/astronomy/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://temuller.github.io/tag/astronomy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>astronomy</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© Tomás Müller `2022`</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://temuller.github.io/images/icon_hu0d997de58f0740f569fcf02a571fbab0_20391_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>astronomy</title>
      <link>https://temuller.github.io/tag/astronomy/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title> Organising my first conference (during a pandemic!)</title>
      <link>https://temuller.github.io/post/student_led_conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://temuller.github.io/post/student_led_conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post was edited by Cristobel Soares. Check 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sepnet.ac.uk/organising-my-first-conference-during-a-pandemic/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt; for the SEPnet version of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sepnet.ac.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SEPnet&lt;/a&gt; provides an opportunity to a group of postgraduate researchers to organise a two-day student-led conference at the University of Southampton. I first came to know about this when I applied for a talk at the Astronomy conference from 2019 (
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sepnet.ac.uk/call-for-abstracts-from-infinity-to-zero-the-history-of-the-universe-in-redshift-3-5-april-2019/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;From Infinity to Zero: the history of the Universe in redshift&lt;/a&gt;). These types of conferences are perfect for early career researchers as it is organised by students, for students, although a few academic speakers are also invited. You do not feel the same pressure as with the big international conferences where you find all the “big names” from your research field. In addition, you also get to know lots of people in the same career stages as you and share experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the 2019 conference I attended was over, I got very interested in organising one of my own. I talked to &lt;strong&gt;Elizabeth Swann&lt;/strong&gt;, University of Portsmouth, the lead organiser to ask her for advice (this was really helpful!). I got very excited with the idea, so I decided to ask around in my Astronomy department for fellow PGRs who might be interested in organising a conference and started writing a proposal. At the same time a group of PGRs from the University of Hertfordshire were writing one of their own. They kindly suggested to work together instead of competing, so we started collaborating on a single proposal (after all, isn’t this what research is all about?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing the topic of the conference was relatively easy. As many big telescopes and surveys are coming in the near future, we thought it might be a good idea to focus on big data and machine learning, thus, the title of the conference: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/view/the-big-data-era-in-astronomy/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Big Data Era in Astronomy&lt;/a&gt;. Finding academic speakers wasn’t too hard either. As several of us in the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/view/the-big-data-era-in-astronomy/committee&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;organising committee&lt;/a&gt; work on different fields, we quickly came up with a list of candidates. &lt;strong&gt;Cristobel Soares&lt;/strong&gt;, Graduate Network Manager, was in charge of the logistics and  funding and very helpful with her advice and support. We mainly had to focus on the structure, science and social events (eg, a conference dinner) at the meeting. Everything was going according to plan as the conference date was approaching, however, everything changed when the COVID-19 pandemic struck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many things were quite uncertain at that time. We didn’t know how long and how much this pandemic would affect everyone, so we had to postpone the conference. As time passed, we grew impatient. We didn’t know if we were going to have the opportunity to host the meeting or if we would have to cancel it. Eventually, we decided to do what many other conferences, schools and workshops were doing, choose a new date and go virtual!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was full of challenges. We didn’t have to worry about funding, conference dinner and other logistics, but we did have to think about the proper platforms to host our virtual conference on. Thankfully, all SEPnet universities have access to Microsoft Teams, so we chose it as our platform for hosting the talks. In addition, Slack is widely used in academic environments as it is perfect for asynchronous discussions, questions, announcements, etc. We also decided to use Slido for the questions at the end of each talk, which was quite new to all of us. I actually got to know about Slido during an 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eso.org/public/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ESO&lt;/a&gt; conference I attended in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, as things were still uncertain close to the new date of the conference in September, many of the students were unable to attend. Therefore, we had to shorten the length of the conference from two days to one and cut the number of sessions by half. However, the conference turned out better than expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the feedback from the participants we learnt that the length of the conference (including the length of talks, breaks, etc.) worked well. Furthermore, the platforms used (Microsoft Teams, Slack, Slido) were really useful and the attendees found the conference was worth attending. Nonetheless, most of them, given the opportunity to choose, would prefer an in-person meeting instead of a virtual one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> Judging a book by its cover: estimating red supergiant masses from their surface abundance</title>
      <link>https://temuller.github.io/post/astrobites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://temuller.github.io/post/astrobites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;See below a guest post I wrote for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobites.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Astrobites&lt;/a&gt;. For the original one 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobites.org/2019/01/28/judging-book-cover-red-supergiant/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1811.04087.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The surface abundances of Red Supergiants at core-collapse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ben Davies and Luc Dessart&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author&amp;rsquo;s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Astrophysics Research Institute, Liverpool John Moores University&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Status:&lt;/strong&gt; accepted for publication in MNRAS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Core-Collapse supernovae (CCSNe) are explosions coming from massive stars (above 8 solar masses) when they reach the end of their life. A 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://astronomy.swin.edu.au/cosmos/T/Type&amp;#43;II&amp;#43;Supernova&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Type II-P Supernova&lt;/a&gt; (SN II-P)  is a common type of CCSN which shows a &amp;ldquo;plateau&amp;rdquo; in its light curve, driven by a Hydrogen-rich envelope. Observations of the explosion site of some of these objects have shown that the progenitors of these explosions are 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://aasnova.org/2018/01/03/astrophysics-of-red-supergiants/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Red Supergiant&lt;/a&gt; (RSG) stars. From these data several predictions can be made by comparing with stellar evolution models. One test that can be made is to determine the initial mass of the progenitor (the mass at the Main-Sequence), which can be done by comparing the luminosity of the progenitor with model predictions. Another way is to measure the mass of the Hydrogen-rich envelope by modelling the light curve and making some assumptions about the core mass. A different way is to measure 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://astrobites.org/guides/spectroscopy-and-spectral-lines/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;spectral lines&lt;/a&gt; of some elements, like Oxygen, at late time (more than 120 days after the explosion, approximately), which correlates with the initial mass as shown by some models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, these methods do not agree in general, so a proper estimation of the initial mass of the progenitor of a SN II-P can not be made. Having this in mind, the authors of the article proposed a different way of estimating the initial mass by measuring the surface composition (or surface abundance) of the progenitor star at early epochs (less than 1 day approximately). There are two main reasons for this: firstly, at this stage some spectral features are easy to identify, and secondly, the surface abundance is not expected to suffer from explosive mixing at early time, which erases any link to the progenitor mass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test this, the authors make use of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://mesa.sourceforge.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MESA&lt;/a&gt; code to study sets of evolutionary models. The evolution across the 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://astronomy.swin.edu.au/cosmos/H/Hertzsprung-Russell&amp;#43;Diagram&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hertzsprung-Russell&lt;/a&gt; (H-R) diagram is key to understand the different processes and phases a star goes through, so the authors use MESA to evolve stars with different initial masses to study this. As it can be seen in Figure 1, less massive stars cross the H-R diagram more rapidly than more massive star, which means that more massive stars have more time to dredge up material from the inner layers into the surface (mixing the abundances) before the end of the RSG phase. Another factor that has to be taken into account is the mass loss. In general, more massive star loose more mass than the least massive ones, so their outer envelopes are thinner compared to the total size of the star, hence their surface abundances suffer from more mixing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Fig1.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fig. 1: H-R diagram for stars with different initial masses as labelled. The circles mark evenly-spaced time steps. The stars indicate the beginning of the RSG phase. More massive stars take longer to cross the H-R diagram than less massive stars.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the surface abundance can not be directly measured, an indirect way of measurement was developed. The authors demonstrate that the surface abundance can be estimated by measuring the ratio between spectral lines, specifically the Carbon-to-Nitrogen ratio, a few hours after the supernova explosion. They simulate early time supernova spectra coming from stars with three different initial masses. The results of these simulated spectra are shown in Figure 2 for a 15 and 25 solar masses stars, for three epochs: 3.1, 12.0 and 24.0 hours after the explosion. One can clearly see the greater strength of Nitrogen lines in the higher mass model, and the greater strength of Carbon and Oxygen lines in the lower mass model. These same trends have been seen in the observed early-time spectra of SN II-P, however, the lack of data at these early stages is clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Fig2.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fig. 2: Early-time SN II-P spectra for progenitors of 15 (blue) and 25 (red) solar masses. From top to bottom, spectra of 3.1, 12.0 and 24.0 hours after explosion. It can be seen the difference in the strengths of lines for the two progenitors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the other methods mentioned above, the surface abundance method suffers from several uncertainties, but no further comparison is given. Finally, the author estimate that within the next decade several early time spectra of SN II-P should be available, which would help decreasing the uncertainties for a better estimation of the initial masses of their progenitors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
